Guide to the Lewis and Lois Gilbert Papers>
Yale University Divinity School Library
Lewis and Lois Gilbert Papers
1925-1980
RG 144
Yale University Divinity School Library
2.5
(6 boxes)
Letters and photographs provide documentation of religious and political conditions in North China from 1929 to 1941 and document Lewis Gilbert's work at Yali 1925-1926. Lewis and Lois Gilbert were missionaries in North China from 1929 to 1941 serving under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions. Lewis Gilbert was also an instructor at Yali, Yale-in-China, Changsha from 1925 to 1926.
Gilbert, Lewis Loder, 1898-1978
Gilbert, Lois Chandler
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Josephine Cowin Gilbert.
Biographical / Historical
1898 Lewis Loder Gilbert born in New Haven, CT
1920 Graduated from Wesleyan University
1923 B.D., Yale Divinity School
1924 Married Lois Chandler
1925 Went to China as instructor in Religion at Yali, Yale-in-China, Changsha, Hunan Province
1927-1929 Enforced home visit
1929 Returned to China, attending language school in Peking, and then serving the ABCFM in Lintsing and Tehchow
1935-1936 Furlough
1936-1941 Work in Tehchow, Tientsin, T'ungchow
1946 Plans to return to China as professor of New Testament at Cheeloo University were abandoned because of health problem. Gilbert was involved in UCC work in Ohio, Vermont and Massachusetts until his retirement.
1969 Lois Chandler Gilbert died
1970 Married Josephine Cowin
1978 Died in Oberlin, Ohio
Scope and Contents
The Gilbert papers provide valuable documentation of religious and political conditions in North China from 1929 to 1941, and document Lewis' work at Yali, 1925-1926. The original handwritten or typed letters of Series I are primarily from Lewis and Lois Gilbert in China to their families in the U.S. The bound letter copybooks of Series II contain primarily letters from Lewis Gilbert to family members. A few of the earlier volumes also include listings of headlines from Chinese newspapers. The bound volumes of correspondence of Series III were edited and compiled by Josephine Cowin Gilbert and have photographic illustrations interspersed.
Arrangement
I. Original Letters, 1925-1941
II. Letter Copybooks, 1937-1941
III. Compiled Volumes, 1925-1980
IV. Biographical Documentation, 1925-1926, n.d.
V. Addendum: 2010, 1925-1946, n.d.
Missions -- China; Gilbert, Lewis Loder, 1898-1978; Gilbert, Lois Chandler; American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions -- China; Yale-in-China Association
- Original Letters, 1925-1941; Series I
  - Primarily from Lewis and Lois Gilbert in China to their families in the U.S, 1925 Aug-1934 Mar (Box 1, Folder 1-12)
  - Primarily from Lewis and Lois Gilbert in China to their families in the U.S, 1935 Jan - 1941 Apr (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
- Letter Copybooks, 1937-1941; Series II
  - Volume 1, 1937 May-Aug (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Volume 2, 1937 Aug-Dec (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Volume 3, 1937 Dec - 1938 Jul (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Volume 4, 1938 Jul-Dec (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Volume 5, 1938 Dec - 1939 Jun (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Volume 6, 1929 Jun - 1940 Jan (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Volume 7, 1940 Jan-Sep (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Volume 8, 1940 Sep - 1941 May (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Compiled Volumes, 1925-1980; Series III
  - Volume I. Changsha, 1925 (Box 3)
  - Volume II. Changsha, 1926 (Box 3)
  - Volume III. Peking, 1929-1930 (Box 3)
  - Volume IV. Lintsing, 1930-1931 (Box 3)
  - Volume V. Lintsing, 1931-1932 (Box 3)
  - Volume VI. Lintsing, 1932 (Box 3)
  - Volume VII. Lintsing, 1933 (Box 3)
  - Volume VIII. Tehchow, 1934 (Box 3)
  - Volume IX. Tehchow, 1934 (Box 4)
  - Volume X. Tehchow, 1936-1937 (Box 4)
  - Volume XI. Tientsin/ Hopei, 1937 (Box 4)
  - Volume XII. Tientsin, Tehchow/ T'ungchow, 1938 (Box 4)
  - Volume XIII. Tehlin/ T'ungchow, 1939 (Box 4)
  - Volume XIV. Tehchow, 1939-1940 (Box 4)
  - Volume XV. T'ungchow and out, 1940-1941 (Box 4)
  - Volume XVI. Appendix, 1938-1980 (Box 4)
- Biographical Documentation, 1925-1926, n.d; Series IV
  - Journal: "How We Got to China", 1925-1926 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Biographical statement re. Lewis Gilbert written by Josephine Gilbert, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Addendum - 2010, 1925-1946, n.d.; Series V
  - Correspondence
    - Printed circular letters of Lewis and Lois Gilbert, 1930-1941 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Typescript circular letters of Lewis Gilbert written from Hsiachin and Lintsing, Shantung, incl. re. Japanese occupying troops, flood relief efforts, 1938, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Typescript letters from Lewis Gilbert to American Board office in Boston, incl. re. flood relief efforts in Lintsing area, 1939 Aug, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Typescript letter fragments, probably from Lewis Gilbert, incl. to Earle Ballou, 1938, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Circular letters and bulletins from other missionaries: Arthur Allen family, Earle Ballou, Albert and Clara Hausske, Lucia Lyons, Alice Murphy, David Paton, Alice Reed, 1934-1942 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Circular letters and bulletins from other missionaries: Harold W. Robinson (including long letter re. political situation in Tehchow, Shantung area in 1938), Robert Whitaker, unidentified, 1937-1940 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Circular letters from Yale-in-China missionaries Phillips Greene and William Pettus, one issue of Yali News Bulletin, 1934, 1941-1942 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, newsclippings, and commentary re. "Tehchow Incident" in which an American Board missionary doctor Francis F. Tucker shot and killed a thief who was stealing items from the mission hospital, 1931 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Collected material
    - Typescript documents re. Sino-Japanese situation in northern China, 1932-1940 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous typescript documents, including autobiography of H.C. Li, translated by L.L. Gilbert, and "The Grace of God Comes to the Flood Victims" by Chou Ming Lin, translated by Lucia Lyons, 1942, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Pamphlets and reports, including: "To Our Friends from Alice and Willard Simpson, Horticultural Experiment Station, East Cliff, Peitaiho Beach China / How May Chinese Agriculture Be Improved?", "The Anti-Christian Movement" (A collection of papers originally issued by the Anti-Christian Movment and translated for the Student Young Men's and Young Women's Christian Associations of China, Shanghai, 1925); "The American Board in Shantung" by Luella Miner; ""A Statement to Chinese Friends" by a group of Nanking missionaries (re. Nanking Affair, 1927); "Constitution of the North China Christian Rural Fellowship"; Report of the Peking Union Bible Training Institute for Women (1941), 1925-1941, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Poster: with translation "If the Communist Devil does not die wild turmoil can never end - To tolerate Communism and oppose Japan is the destruction of China. Awake quickly and establish a happy land."; schematic map of American Board mission in Paotingfu, ca. 1938, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions (ABCFM): China Bulletin, 1942-1945 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - ABCFM: China newsletter, Harold Matthews, 1945-1946 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - ABCFM: Post-War Japan Bulletin, Alice Cary, 1945-1946 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - ABCFM: Reports and letters, including regarding North China Christian Rural Service Union, "The Mission Mirror", "Report of Visitation in the North" by E.L. Chapple, Auburndale Missionary Conference, North China Kung Li Hui, China Committee, 1935-1942 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - ABCFM, Reports and letters, including to/from Wynn C. Fairfield, report on Lu Ho Middle School, Sian, Shensi, 1943-1945 Mar (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - ABCFM: Reports and letters, including from Harold Matthew, re. reestablishment of North China mission after war, North China Christian Rural Service Union, 1945 Apr- Nov (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - ABCFM: Reports and letters, including from Harold Matthew, re. reestablishment of North China mission after war, relief work in the Te-Lin area, 1945 Dec- 1946 Jan (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - ABCFM: Circular letters of individuals, including Earle Ballou, Grace Boynton, Margaret Dow, Elmer Galt, Albert Hausske, Samuel Leger, Alice Reed, Harold Robinson, 1940s (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
    - National Christian Council of China (NCCC): radio broadcast transcripts, 1937-1941 (Box 5, Folder 10-16)
    - NCCC: News Bulletin, Alice Gregg, 1938 Jun -1940 Mar (Box 5, Folder 17-18)
    - NCCC: Letters and reports, 1937-1940, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 19)